Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5204 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- September 1938 to December 1938, and Undated 1938. (Reel 9)
  - November, 1938, 3 (Reel 9)
    A major topic during this month is the letter sent out by three former STFU officials -- Claude Williams, E.B. McKinney, and W.L. Blackstone -- protesting their expulsion from the union and enclosing a mimeographed ten-point program for the union (1,12). There is an exchange between Butler and Henderson in which Henderson agreed to stay neutral in the Williams dispute (1,7). There is further correspondence with the WDL on the "Night-Riding" cases (1,4,7) and with UCAPAWA officials over the agreement for paying back dues (1,12,14,30). The Southern Conference for Human Welfare met in Birmingham on November 20 to 23; the papers include the program, a printed copy of the Proceedings, and a press release on labor's role in the Conference (20). Lastly, there is a report on an STFU-inspired "Buyer's Club" (Consumer Cooperative) at Blytheville, Ark. (11)
  - December, 1938, 4 (Reel 9)
    Two conventions in one month kept the STFU membership busy during December. The UCAPAWA convention was held in San Francisco on December 12 to 16; the papers include Henderson's report to the convention (12), reports from UCAPAWA Districts 1, 2, 5, 7, and 9 (12), a resolution introduced by the STFU delegates (12), and two letters from Mitchell to Evelyn Smith describing the fate of the STFU resolution (13, 15). The STFU Fifth Annual Convention met at Cotton Plant, Arkansas on December 29 to January 1; the papers include a letter from Butler to all delegates, urging them to ignore rumors of danger at Cotton Plant (24); the program, President's Report, minutes (apparently incomplete), a mimeographed copy of the Proceedings, and a report from the STFU delegation to the UCAPAWA convention in San Francisco (29). In other matters, there is an apology and a request for reinstatement addressed to the NEC by E.B. McKinney (5), and a brief letter from Missouri organizer O.H. Whitfield warning Mitchell that 900 families facing eviction on January 1, planned to encamp on a local highway (1)
  - No Date, 1938, 5 (Reel 9)
    Affidavit of Charlie Kelley, held in peonage near Helena, Ark.; "The Condition of Farm Labor on Cotton Plantations in the South and Southwest in 1938", a 3-page typewritten report; Report to the National Executive Committees of the WDL and STFU on the relationship between the two organizations; "Per Capita Payments Made by STFU Texas locals prior to Formation of Texas District"; complete lists of STFU locals in Mississippi, Arkansas, and Missouri; "Suggestions for Organizing Farm Workers Unions in California", by J.B. Nathan, "Rebel Arts Songbook"; "Told by the Sharecroppers", two pages of excerpts from stories told by STFU organizers.
- Miscellaneous Union Business 1938, and January 1939 to February 1939. (Reel 10)
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1938, 1 (Reel 10)
    Folders 321 to 323 -- Not Filmed. Folder 324 -- Local Secretary's Reports (approx. ten items). Folder 325 -- Monthly Reports of Membership and Fees + attached correspondence (approx. two hundred items in rough chronological order). Note: Throughout 1938, local secretaries were required to file these reports in duplicate. The duplicates, however, have been removed from this folder and were not filmed. Folders 326 to 327 -- Not Filmed
  - January, 1939, 2 (Reel 10)
    [Note: Monthly reports from local secretaries are filed in the main chronological series throughout 1939. In all other years, these items will be found in the "Miscellaneous Union Business" section.] On Jan. 1, 1700 sharecroppers evicted from their homes encamped on a US highway near Sikeston, Mo. Many of the refugees were STFU members and the demonstration was led by STFU Second Vice-President O.H. Whitfield.. The reader may follow the progress of the demonstration in a flood of telegrams sent and received by union headquarters throughout the month, in two STFU press releases (14,23), in reports from F.R. Betton (24) and Kester (27), and in letters from a few of the evicted sharecroppers (24,26). See also copies of letters from Albert Jackson (alias "Al Murphy"), a Communist organizer in St. Louis, concerning the demonstration (9, 18), an exchange of telegrams between the STFU and the CIO, requesting the latter to help prevent Jackson from taking over (17), and a 4-page report to the NEC on the situation from the STFU field staff in Mo. (21). A 3-page letter from Donald Henderson, requesting that all dues be paid directly to UCAPAWA (28) elicited a stern letter to all STFU locals ordering them to continue to send dues payments to Memphis (31)
  - February, 1939, 3 (Reel 10)
    Two issues, the Missouri Highway demonstration and the battle with UCAPAWA over STFU autonomy, continued to dominate the correspondence during February. There are a number of important letters throughout the month by and about O.H. Whitfield, who shifted his support from the STFU to UCAPAWA. The papers include reports on the situation in Missouri from organizers F.R. Betton (8, 18) and J.F. Moore (12), as well as a flood of letters from the evicted sharecroppers themselves. One letter from Mitchell to Jack Herling gives especially detailed information on the situation (10). The correspondence also concerns the union's efforts to obtain relief for the demonstrators from Northern contributors and the FSA; in this connection, see the Financial Statement for the Southeast Missouri Relief Fund, which contains a list of contributors (18), and a letter from R.C. Smith, Regional Director of FSA, on his agency's efforts (27). Papers related to the UCAPAWA fight appear throughout the month and include: letters from Donald Henderson to STFU organizers, (23); a four-page mimeographed "Analysis of UCAPAWA" apparently prepared by the STFU (14); a letter from Gardner Jackson, advising Mitchell to comply with Henderson's various requests (21); and approximately 30 returns to an STFU questionnaire on the status and condition of all locals (17).
- March 1939 to June 1939. (Reel 11)
  - March, 1939, 1 (Reel 11)
    The STFU withdrew from UCAPAWA on March 12, and virtually all of the papers for March have to do with the split. A chronology of the correspondence and events leading up to the withdrawal is especially helpful (11). Returns from a membership referendum on withdrawal appear throughout the month. Advice poured in from friends of the union, including Ward Rodgers (3), Howard Kester (3), Gardner Jackson (13,31), Matthew Woll, Third Vice-President of the AF of L (29), and from two AF of L leaders in Texas and California who complained of Communism in the CIO (18, 22). John Brophy, Director of the CIO, attempted to mediate, but his efforts proved of no avail (8 to 11). Three letters from Mitchell are of special interest, one to Butler outlining strategy (3), one to Lucy Randolph Mason stating that the STFU had no quarrel with the CIO itself (30), and a five-page letter to The Nation explaining the STFU side of the controversy (30). Donald Henderson held a special convention in St. Louis to reorganize the Missouri STFU and Joyce Crawford reported on it at length (13). Odis Sweeden reorganized the Oklahoma STFU into the Oklahoma Tenant Farmers Union; the papers include the Constitution and the program adopted at Sweeden's convention (19). The STFU held its own special convention in Memphis on March 19; although the resolutions adopted there do appear (19) there is no record of the Proceedings in the papers. To protect NSW from UCAPAWA, Mitchell and Harriet Young decided to set it up as a non-profit corporation; the papers include the legal forms for incorporation (14, 15, 17)
  - April, 1939, 2 (Reel 11)
    Donald Henderson held a UCAPAWA convention in Memphis on April 2; the papers include a UCAPAWA handbill and an STFU press release on Mitchell's walk-out from the convention (2). Other items related directly to the feud with Henderson include an injunction obtained by the STFU to prevent UCAPAWA from organizing under the STFU's name (5), as well as two long letters from Mitchell to Gardner Jackson and Norman Thomas (3, 10). The Oklahoma STFU was especially weakened by the split; efforts to rebuild it can be traced in field reports from W.R. Purcells and Guy Thomas (1,2,30), as well as in Mitchell's report from Okla. of April 21. The Delta Cooperative Farm hosted a Southern Socialist Conference on April 7 to 9; related items include a mimeographed report on the conference (7) and a long letter from Norman Thomas to the Conference on building the Socialist Party in the South (5). Two union members were beaten by Sheriff's Deputies at Crawfordsville, Ark., on April 15; there is heavy correspondence relating to this outbreak of violence during the remainder of the month, but see especially the affidavits of the victims (24). Correspondence concerning NSW appears throughout the month and includes the Final Financial Statement for 1939 (28). There are a number of replies from the FSA to STFU complaints (20,21,27), and there is scattered correspondence about the union's search for a new Educational Director
  - May, 1939, 3 (Reel 11)
    The work of repairing the union continued during May. Butler prepared an analysis of STFU locals, which unfortunately does not appear in the papers; however, see the covering letters to organizers D.A. Griffin and J.F. Hynds which discuss ways of reviving the locals (8), and Mitchell to Blaine Treadway on the same subject (9). Reports on the rebuilding effort in Oklahoma arrived from W.R. Purcells (13) and Guy Thomas (13, 28). Butler tried to persuade Kester declined, citing his many obligations (10). The union attempted to pressure Prosecuting Attorney Bruce Ivy to investigate the violence at Crawfordsville, but Ivy proved evasive (13,16,26). Also of special interest are two letters from J.E. Clayton on his plan to purchase the Lowden plantation near Gould, Ark. to resettle black sharecroppers (4,6,and June 9) and two long letters from J.C. Thompson, a Louisiana Socialist, commenting on the recent Southern Socialist Conference (15 and June 1). The NEC met on May 13, but no minutes appear
  - June 1939, 4 (Reel 11)
    An exchange of lengthy letters between J.R. Butler and David Clendenin, Secretary-Treasurer of the WDL, covers the main issues which arose during the month (7,9, 14,26). One of those issues was arranging bail for Louis Johnson, a defendant in the "Night-Riding" case which first arose in October, 1938; the papers include a letter from Johnson (17) and a memorandum on the case (n.d. [June, 1939]). Another major issue was a request from the Farm Workers' Allied Union, which had started organizing in the San Joaquin Valley in California, for affiliation with the STFU (19, 23, 28); see especially a report on the new union from J.B. Nathan in San Francisco (28). The NEC met on June 28 and decided to arrange mass meetings throughout STFU territory in hopes of reviving the union; letters to local secretaries arranging such meetings appear during the last three days of June.
- July 1939 to September 1939. (Reel 12)
  - July, 1939, 1 (Reel 12)
    Mitchell and F.R. Betton attended a conference in Mexico, called by Clarence Senior, to study the experiment in cooperative farming underway in the Laguna Region; the papers include a prospectus on the conference and a seven-page mimeographed report by the STFU delegation (6). There is also an extensive report from Priscilla Robertson, a friend of the union, on the Poplar Bluff camp in Missouri (5). The STFU initiated a workers' education project during July; one may follow its progress through the correspondence of Blaine Treadway, STFU Education Director. Toward the end of the month, there is a letter from the National Federation of Colored Farmers, turning down an STFU offer for affiliation (26), and a letter from Mitchell to former CIO official Barney Egan on reorganizing the STFU in Texas (26)
  - August, 1939, 2 (Reel 12)
    With Mitchell working full-time for the National Youth Administration in North Carolina, three members of the NEC wrote Butler suggesting that Mitchell resign as STFU Secretary. Butler informed Mitchell about this and other recent developments (9, 12, 16), but Mitchell refused to resign 914,15). See also F.R. Betton's comments on the dispute (26). A bitter personal controversy arose among the STFU organizers in Oklahoma; one can follow it in the letters of Henry Pippin, Guy Thomas, and W.R. Purcells. Also, in relation to Oklahoma, there are no less than seven letters from former state President Odis L. Sweeden asking Butler to rehire him as an organizer. Butler wrote all locals, asking them to fill out a questionnaire form on the desirability of holding a wage scale conference; Butler also wrote Mitchell on the same day explaining why he opposed such a conference (14). Other items of special interest include: Blaine Treadway to the Farm Workers' Allied Union on possible affiliation (8); and the typescript of a magazine article "Recent Activities of the STFU" by Butler (13)
  - September, 1939, 3 (Reel 12)
    Union member in Southeast Missouri were eager to stage a cotton-pickers' strike, but the STFU leadership decided against it. The reader may follow the debate in the heavy correspondence between headquarters and the STFU field staff (13 to 22), and in two long letters the STFU field staff (13 to 22), and in two long letters explaining the decision against the strike by Butler (22) and Blaine Treadway (23). The NEC met on Sept. 9; the papers include the "opening Remarks", presumably by Butler (9), and the resolutions passed by the Council (10), but the minutes do not appear. Finally, there is a copy of the Constitution of the Farm Workers Allied Union of California (7), and a communication from Frank McCallister on the possibility of arranging a separate CIO character for the STFU (5).
- October 1939 to December 1939, and Undated 1939. (Reel 13)
  - October, 1939, 1 (Reel 13)
    Most of the correspondence this month deals with fund-raising, especially NSW, and with the attempt to reactivate locals. Items of special interest include: "An Open Letter to Friends of the STFU", an 8-page mimeographed statement on the split with UCAPAWA (1); F.R. Betton to the Chicago Defender and the Pittsburg Courier, asking for help in fund-raising and publicity (11, 12); a letter from Butler to inactive locals (20); Butler to J.B. Nathan on the NEC's decision concerning the Farm Workers' Allied Union (23); STFU lawyer Claude Cooper to Butler, on the trial of Louis Johnson (24); affidavit of Henry Johnson, a 77-year old black man forced to leave his town at gunpoint by a Deputy Sheriff (28); and reports on the convention of the National Federation of Colored Farmers from F.R. Betton and D.A. Griffin (31 and Nov. 3)
  - November, 1939, 2 (Reel 13)
    Butler, in a mimeographed letter to all union members dated October 26, gave instructions for a campaign to get STFU representatives elected to AAA county committees. When George Mayberry, a black organizer at Mashulaville, Miss., tried to obtain information about the elections from Noxubee County officials, he was kidnapped, beaten, and run out of town. The papers concerning the case, which run from Nov. 22 onward, include a letter from Mayberry to the union, asking for help (23), Mayberry's affidavit (29), and a long letter from Butler to Secretary of Agriculture Henry A. Wallace on the case (25). Another issue developed around Poplar Bluff encampment in Missouri, where several hundred sharecropper families who had participated in the highway demonstration the previous winter were living under wretched conditions. Harriet Young warned the union of a Communist attempt to start a relief campaign (9), advice for an STFU counteroffensive came from the WDL (13) and Norman Thomas (20), and the union arranged a meeting with FSA Administrator Will Alexander to secure government help (27 to 31). For a report on the overall situation in Missouri, see Butler to Isaac Wells (17). Finally, there are daily reports from F.R. Betton during his organizing trip in Mississippi (14 to 17)
  - December, 1939, 3 (Reel 13)
    Further items relating to the Poplar Bluff camp include a letter from Butler to Josephine Smoot, detailing the efforts being made for the refugees (11) and an STFU press release on the projected FSA program (20). There are replies from two Department of Agriculture officials to union complaints in the Mayberry case, both promising that all AAA county elections will be well-publicized in the future (6, 13). There is an especially important exchange of letters between Mitchell and James E. Sidel, Field Director of the National Child Labor Committee, concerning Donald Henderson's attempt to form a "National Council to Aid Agricultural Workers" in competition with NSW (11, 15). Preparations for the Annual Convention and for NSW, including the hiring of Pauli Murray as Secretary of NSW, occupy much of the correspondence. There is a draft of a revised STFU Constitution, apparently written by A. James McDonald, who sent Butler a long letter concerning the document (15, 27). Lastly, a four-page letter from D. William R. Amberson appears, urging financial austerity and self-sufficiency for the STFU (29)
  - No Date, 1939, 4 (Reel 13)
    Correspondence and telegrams concerning the Missouri highway demonstration and the battle with UCAPAWA; telegram to FSA Administrator Will. W. Alexander on the Poplar Bluff encampment; Report on the "Status of Negro Schools in Mississippi, 1939"; letters from Kester and Frank W. McCulloch
- January 1940 to April 1940. (Reel 14)
  - January, 1940, 1 (Reel 14)
    The Sixth Annual STFU Convention met at Blytheville, Ark. From Jan 5 to 7; the papers include: the Annual Financial Report for 1939; Revised STFU Constitution; Proceedings; STFU Legislative Program for 1940; and "Resolutions Adopted". NEC minutes appear both before and after the Convention (4, 8). Further evictions of share-croppers in Missouri led Governor Lloyd Stark to form a "Southeast Missouri Landowners-Tenants-Sharecroppers Conference". The STFU, through correspondence with the Governor and Bishop Billiam Scarlett of St. Louis, successfully sought representation on the committee (3,10,18,20). There is also much correspondence with Missouri locals and with the FSA on the plight of the evicted families, including an outline of the FSA's five-point program for meeting the crisis (16). Members of the STFU local at the Dyess Colony in Arkansas complained to the union about the project's management, and the STFU got FSA Administrator Will Alexander to begin an investigation (13, 19, 23, 25). Complaints also came from the Delta Cooperative Farm; see Kester to Butler about the Trustees' plans to investigate (19). Lastly, there is a report on the status of the educational program by STFU Education Director Evelyn Smith (31)
  - February, 1940, 2 (Reel 14)
    Items related to the Dyess Colony investigation include two reports from Floyd Slayton, Secretary of the Dyess local (6, 14) and a list of grievances submitted to the FSA (22). There is an exchange of correspondence between Kester, Butler, and Blaine Treadway on the Delta Cooperative Farm inquiry. The reader may follow developments in Southeast Missouri through the correspondence with Jewel Mayes, the Chairman of Gov. Stark's special commission (5,9,10), through reports on the situation from STFU organizers W.M. Tanner and D.A. Griffin (12, 13, 20), and through a report from the Missouri State Employment Service based on its own report survey (13). There are several lengthy letters to and from Pauli Murray concerning plans for NSW, as well as one from Morris Milgram of the WDL to Butler on raising funds in Hollywood (21). The STFU sent a delegation to Washington from Feb. 29 to March 1 for a variety of purposes; the papers include the delegation's schedule (March 1) and materials relating to the delegation's appearance before the Senate Sub-Committee on Agriculture (27, March 1). Gardner Jackson sent out a letter to all sponsors of NSW, asking them to support UCAPAWA instead (24); Mitchell, Walter White, and Benjamin Marsh of The People's Lobby all replied immediately (27, 28). Final items of special interest are: a memorandum from Mitchell to the CIO, entitled "An Organizing Committee for Migratory Workers" (10); and To Establish Justice: Sharecroppers Under Planters Law, a booklet by Howard Kester (8)
  - March, 1940, 3 (Reel 14)
    National Sharecroppers Week was held from March 4 to 10; papers relating to it include: the schedule of events and speakers (1); mimeographed instructions to local sponsors (4); reports on NSW in Los Angeles from Mary E. Gallagher (12,23); and reports on UCAPAWA efforts to disrupt NSW from Alfred Baker Lewis (18), William R. Amberson (19), and Purnell Benson (19). There is an exchange of correspondence between Gardner Jackson and Frank Crosswaith, head of the Negro Labor Committee, concerning Jackson's Feb. 24 letter to NSW sponsors (5,8,15,18). A dispute arose between Mitchell and Arthur G. McDowell, Labor Secretary of the Socialist Party, concerning Mitchell's negotiations with Lee Pressman of the CIO about possible STFU affiliation (7 to 27). At the end of the month, reports of racial violence arrived from Mississippi and the union lodged a complaint with the Justice Department (28); an affidavit from one of the victims of the violence appears on April 4
  - April, 1940, 4 (Reel 14)
    Investigations into complaints from union members at the Dyess Colony and the Delta Cooperative Farm was a major topic of correspondence in April. On the DCF inquiry, see especially Blaine Treadway to the DCF local (6); on the Dyess situation, see the reports from Floyd Slayton (March 19, 4, 6, 9) and Butler's letter to the Dyess local (23). The union sent a delegation to a convention of the Southern Conference for Human Welfare; the papers include the call, a "confidential report" by SP Southern Secretary Frank McCallister, and a report by STFU organizer D.A> Griffin (14). Finally, there is a "Memorandum to Sponsors and Friends" of NSW on the UCAPAWA attempt at sabotage (3).
- May 1940 to October 1940. (Reel 15)
  - May, 1940, 1 (Reel 15)
    May was a month of rebuilding for the union. Letters went out to all state organizers, commenting on the problems in their respective states (1). The DCF investigating committee met on May 10 and issued a report (11). There is an especially interesting exchange of letters between Mitchell and Butler, with Mitchell insisting upon a campaign to organize migrant workers as a means of reviving the union (14, 17, 23, 25); see also Mitchell's attempt to write a life history of a migrant worker 921). Two letters appear from Constance Rumbough, Southern Secretary of the Fellowship of Reconciliation, on initiating a campaign against the poll tax in Tennessee (6, 10).
  - June, 1940, 2 (Reel 15)
    Reports arrived from W. M. Tanner and others in Missouri that the WPA was laying off workers to aid planters in obtaining cotton choppers at a lower wage; see especially Tanner's affidavit on the matter (6). Reports from locals in Mississippi are especially plentiful this month. Beginning in June, a monthly listing of "Amounts Remitted by STFU Locals" appears along with the monthly financial statement; these lists provide a good picture of the strength and geographical distribution of the union
  - July, 1940, 3 (Reel 15)